Finding Aid for Medical School (University of Michigan) records, 1850-2010
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
- Dean's Records 1915-1996
  - Departmental Files 1959-1996
    - 1956-1984
      - Pediatrics
        - General 1960-1984, 3 folders (Box 164)
        - Adolescent Medicine-Mott 1979 (Box 164)
        - Neonatology 1979-1981 (Box 164)
        - Pediatric Cardiology 1979-1984 (Box 164)
      - Physical Medicine and Rehabilitation 1976-1984 (Box 164)
      - Physiology
        - General 1960-1968 (Box 164)
        - General 1978-1981 (Box 164)
      - Postgraduate Medicine and Health Professions Education
        - General 1972-1984, 3 folders (Box 165)
        - Affiliated Hospitals 1970-1984 (Box 165)
        - Allied Health Education 1971-1982 (Box 165)
        - Learning Resource Center 1984 (Box 165)
        - Medical and Biological Education 1959-1984 (Box 165)
      - Psychiatry
        - General 1956-1984, 4 folders (Box 165)
        - CPH Expansion 1969-1970 (Box 165)
        - Dr. Frank Ochberg 1981 (Box 165)
        - Dr. Selma Fraiberg 1979-1981 (Box 165)
      - Radiation Oncology 1981-1984 (Box 166)
      - Radiology
        - General 1963-1969, 1974, 1977-1984, 4 folders (Box 166)
        - Nuclear Magnetic Resonance 1980-1984 (Box 166)
      - Surgery
        - General 1960-1972, 1974-1984, 3 folders (Box 166)
        - Budget 1973-1984 (Box 166)
        - Emergency Medicine
          - General 1973-1983, 2 folders (Box 166)
          - MSP Bylaws 1979-1981 (Box 166)
        - General Surgery
          - General 1966-1984 (Box 166)
          - Medical Service Plan 1977-1984 (Box 166)
        - Neurosurgery
          - General 1969-1983 (Box 167)
          - Head Protection Laboratory 1980-1982 (Box 167)
          - Medical Service Plan 1978-1979 (Box 167)
        - Oral Surgery 1958-1965 (Box 167)
        - Orthopedic Surgery
          - General 1973-1984 (Box 167)
          - Medical Service Plan 1976-1977 (Box 167)
        - Pediatric Surgery
          - General 1973-1984 (Box 167)
          - Medical Service Plan 1976-1977 (Box 167)
        - Plastic Surgery
          - General 1961-1965, 1975-1984, 2 folders (Box 167)
          - Medical Service Plan 1977-1978 (Box 167)
        - Thoracic Surgery 1967-1984, 2 folders (Box 167)
        - Urology
          - General 1966-1983 (Box 167)
          - Medical Service Plan 1979 (Box 167)
    - 1977-1990
      Departmental Files, 1977-1990 subseries (1994 Accession) spans from 1977 to 1990 although the bulk of the files are concentrated in the period 1985-1989. Material in these files includes reports, correspondence, memorandums, and other information received from the departments and units which constitute the Medical School. Files typically include budgetary and staffing information as well as correspondence to and from the chairperson regarding research projects and departmental activities.
      - Anatomy and Cell Biology
        - General 1985-1989 (Box 213)
        - Chairman Review 1982 (Box 238)
      - Anesthesiology
        - General 1985-1989, 3 folders (Box 213)
        - House Officer Issues 1989 (Box 213)
        - Adams, Alfred 1986-1988 (Box 238)
          [PR RESTRICTED until July 1, 2018 ]
        - Cohen, Peter 1984 (Box 238)
        - Finch, Jay 1986-1987 (Box 238)
          [PR RESTRICTED until July 1, 2017 ]
      - Biological Chemistry 1985-1989, 3 folders (Box 213)
      - Dermatology
        - General 1985-1989, 5 folders (Box 213)
        - Retin A 1989-1990 (Box 213)
      - Family Practice 1985-1989, 5 folders (Box 213)
      - Human Genetics 1985-1989 (Box 213)
      - Internal Medicine
        - General 1985-1989, 5 folders (Box 217)
        - Arthritis Research Training Center 1987-1988 (Box 217)
        - Diabetes Research and Training Center
          - General 1985-1988 (Box 217)
          - Upjohn Site Visit 1988 (Box 217)
        - Human Gene Therapy 1988-1989, 2 folders (Box 217)
        - Infectious Disease 1986 (Box 217)
        - MSRB Funding 1988 (Box 217)
        - Kaiser Faculty Scholar Visit 1988 (Box 238)
        - Nabel, Gary 1989 (Box 238)
        - Nuclear Medicine 1984-1989 (Box 218)
          - Wahl Grant Approval 1986-1989 (Box 218)
        - Lyubica Dalbach 1984-1986 (Box 238)
          [PR RESTRICTED until July 1, 2016 ]
        - Ronald Natale 1983 (Box 238)
        - John Nicklas 1989-1990 (Box 238)
          [PR RESTRICTED until July 1, 2020 ]
        - David Wilber 1985-1986 (Box 238)
      - Microbiology and Immunology
        - General 1985-1989, 2 folders (Box 218)
        - Howard Brickner 1985-1986 (Box 238)
      - Neurology 1985-1989, 2 folders (Box 218)
      - Obstetrics and Gynecology
        - General 1985-1989, 5 folders (Box 218)
        - 5 Year Plan 1988 (Box 218)
        - Dr. Jonathan Ayres 1988-1989 (Bates/Beer Professorship) 1978-1984 (Box 238)
          [PR RESTRICTED until July 1, 2019 ]
        - Dr. Preston V. Dilts (chairman) 1988 (Box 238)
        - Radiation/Ultrasound 1986-1988 (Box 218)
        - Dr. James Martin 1984-1985 (Box 238)
      - Ophthalmology 1985-1989, 2 folders (Box 218)
      - Otolaryngology 1985-1989, 2 folders (Box 219)
      - Pathology
        - General 1985-1989, 3 folders (Box 219)
        - Godfrey D. Stobbe Professorship 1985-1987 (Box 219)
      - Pediatrics and Communicable Diseases
        - General 1985-1989, 4 folders (Box 219)
        - Bone Marrow Transplant Program 1986 (Box 219)
        - Retreat 1989 (Box 219)
        - Dr. Golder Wilson 1982-1983 (Box 238)
        - Dr. William J. Oliver Resignation 1979 (Box 238)
      - Pharmacology 1980-1989, 2 folders
        - Folder 1 (Box 219)
        - Folder 2 (Box 238)
      - Physical Medicine and Rehabilitation (Box 220)
        - General 1985-1989, 4 folders (Box 220)
        - Dr. Ted Cole 1987-1988 (Box 238)
      - Postgraduate Medicine and Health Professions Education
        - General 1985-1989, 2 folders (Box 220)
        - Budget 1977-1984 (Box 220)
        - Biomedical Communication Program Review 1987 (Box 220)
        - Biomedical Illustration 1985-1989, 2 folders (Box 220)
      - Physiology 1984-1989, 2 folders (Box 220)
      - Psychiatry (Box 221)
        - General 1985-1989, 5 folders (Box 221)
        - Substance Abuse Center 1985-1989, 3 folders (Box 221)
        - Dr. Robert Friedel (Chairman) 1984-1985 (Box 221)
        - Dr. Monica Starkman 1984 (Box 238)
        - Dr. Maria Paluszny 1983-1985 (Box 238)
      - Radiation Oncology
        - General 1985-1989, 2 folders (Box 221)
        - Alice Crocker Lloyd Project. 1986 (Box 221)
      - Radiology
        - General 1985-1989, 3 folders (Box 222)
        - MRI Acquisition 1985-1986 (Box 222)
        - Barbara Threatt/Breast Cancer Detection Center 1978-1986 (Box 222)
      - Surgery
        - General 1985-1989, 5 folders (Box 222)
        - Lithotripter 1985-1986 (Box 222)
        - Pediatric Surgery 1985-1988 (Box 222)
        - Sports Medicine 1980-1986 (Box 222)
      - ULAM (Unit for Laboratory Animal Medicine) 1985-1990, 2 folders (Box 222)
    - 1978, 1981-1996
      The 1978, 1981-1996 Departmental Files subseries (2002 Accession, 10 linear feet) specifically documents the dean's interactions with each of the individual departments of the Medical School. The series includes records from the tenures of dean Giles Bole (1991-1996) and interim dean A. Lorris Betz (1996-1998), as well as files created during the tenure of dean Joseph Johnson III that were retained by Bole when he became interim dean in 1990. The highlight of the subseries is its detailed information on the departments, including their budget, hiring, promotion, and space allocation processes; their growth and/or struggles with cost containment and the move to managed care; and their political maneuverings, collaborations, and occasional tensions with other departments and units of the university.
      - Anatomy and Cell Biology
        - General 1990-1996, 6 folders (Box 275)
        - External Review 1996-1997 (Box 275)
        - Grievances 1990 (Box 284)
      - Anesthesiology
        - General 1990-1996, 6 folders (Box 275)
        - Personnel 1990-1991 (Box 284)
          [PR RESTRICTED until July 1, 2021 ]
      - Biological Chemistry 1990-1996, 6 folders
        - Personnel 1990-1996 (Box 284)
          [PR RESTRICTED until July 1, 2026 ]
      - Dermatology
        - General 1990-1996, 6 folders (Box 275)
        - Johnson and Johnson Contract, Jan-September 1990 (Box 275)
        - Johnson and Johnson Contract October 1990-1992 (Box 276)
        - Personnel 1993-1996 (Box 284)
        - Review 1995-1997 (Box 276)
      - Diversity: Departmental Outreach Programs 1991 (Box 276)
      - Family Practice
        - General 1990-1996, 7 folders (Box 276)
        - Personnel 1990-1992 (Box 284)
          [PR RESTRICTED until July 1, 2022 ]
        - Review 1996 (Box 276)
      - Human Genetics
        - General 1990-1996, 6 folders (Box 276)
        - Review 1996 (Box 276)
        - Center for Gene Therapy 1995-1997 (Box 276)
      - Internal Medicine
        - General 1989-June 1991, 2 folders (Box 276)
        - General July 1991-1996, 7 folders (Box 277)
        - Clinical Research Center 1989-1990 (Box 277)
        - Clinical Research Center 1991-1996, 6 folders (Box 278)
        - Clinical Research Center Director Search 1990 (Box 284)
        - Gary Nabel Retention 1995 (Box 278)
        - Nuclear Medicine 1990-1991 (Box 278)
        - Personnel 1991-1996 (Box 284)
      - Microbiology and Immunology
        - General 1990-1996, 6 folders (Box 278)
        - Personnel 1992-1993 (Box 284)
          [PR RESTRICTED until July 1, 2023 ]
      - Neurology
        - General 1990-1996, 6 folders (Box 278)
        - Markey Grant Annual Reports 1991-1992 (Box 278)
        - Neural and Behavioral Sciences Course Review 1987-1988 (Box 284)
        - L. Cass Terry Lawsuit 1989-1990 (Box 284)
          [CR RESTRICTED until July 1, 2090 ]
      - Obstetrics and Gynecology
        - General 1990-1996, 6 folders (Box 278)
        - Review and Chair Change 1991-1992 (Box 284)
      - Ophthalmology (Box 279)
        - General 1990-1996, 6 folders (Box 279)
        - Review 1994 (Box 279)
      - Otolaryngology
        - General 1990-1996, 6 folders (Box 279)
        - Search Committee 1992-1993 (Box 284)
      - Pathology
        - General 1990-1996, 6 folders (Box 279)
        - A. Rees Midgely 1991 (Box 284)
        - Personnel 1994 (Box 284)
          [PR RESTRICTED until July 1, 2024 ]
        - Tissue Typing 1989-1990 (Box 279)
      - Pediatrics 1990-1992, 3 folders (Box 279)
      - Pediatrics 1993-1996, 4 folders (Box 280)
      - Pharmacology
        - General 1990-1996, 6 folders (Box 280)
        - Grievances 1994 (Box 284)
      - Physical Medicine and Rehabilitation
        - General 1990-1996, 6 folders (Box 280)
        - Personnel 1990-1991 (Box 309)
        - Review 1991 (Box 281)
      - Physiology
        - General 1990-1996, 5 folders (Box 281)
        - Intra-Departmental Conflict 1990-1992 (Box 309)
      - Postgraduate Medicine and Health Professionals Education (PGM)
        - PGM 1989-1994, 1996, 6 folders (Box 281)
        - Biomedical Communications 1990 (Box 281)
        - Graduate Medical Education 1990-1991 (Box 281)
        - PGM Review 1995-1996 (Box 281)
      - Psychiatry
        - General 1989-1992, 3 folders (Box 281)
        - Psychiatry 1993-1996, 4 folders (Box 282)
        - Budget Meeting 1/21/1991 (Box 282)
        - Mental Health Research Institute 1990-1993, 1995-1996, 3 folders (Box 282)
        - Negotiations 1978, 1989 (Box 282)
        - Review--Internal Report 1992 (Box 282)
        - Review--Materials for External Consultants 1996 (Box 282)
        - Substance Abuse Center 1988-1990 (Box 282)
      - Radiation Oncology 1990-1994, 4 folders (Box 282)
      - Radiation Oncology 1995-1996 (Box 283)
      - Radiology
        - General 1990-1996, 6 folders (Box 283)
        - William Martel. 1981-1993 (Box 284)
        - Personnel 1992-1993 (Box 284)
        - Research MRI 1995 (Box 283)
      - Surgery
        - General 1990-1996, 7 folders (Box 283)
        - ER 1990 (Box 283)
        - Oral Surgery (Dentistry) 1983, 1986-1990 (Box 283)
        - Orthopedics
          - General 1995-1996 (Box 283)
          - Personnel 1991 (Box 284)
        - Patient Information 1990-1991, 1996 (Box 284)
          [CR RESTRICTED until July 1, 2096 ]
        - Prostate Institute 1994 (Box 283)
      - Medicine (ULAM) 1990-1996, 6 folders (Box 283)
      - Anatomy
        - Grievances 1990 (open July 1, 2020) (Box 283)
      - Anesthesiology
        - Personnel 1990-1991 (open July 1, 2021) (Box 283)
      - Biological Chemistry
        - Personnel 1990-1996 (open July 1, 2026) (Box 283)
      - Dermatology
        - Personnel 1993-1996 (open July 1, 2026) (Box 283)
      - Family Practice
        - Personnel 1990-1992 (open July 1, 2022) (Box 283)
      - Internal Medicine
        - Personnel 1991-1996 (open July 1, 2026) (Box 283)
        - Clinical Research Center Director Search 1990 (open July 1, 2020) (Box 283)
      - Microbiology and Immunology
        - Personnel 1992-1993 (open July 1, 2023) (Box 283)
      - Neurology Neural and Behavioral Sciences
        - Course Review 1987-1988 (open July 1, 2018) (Box 283)
        - L. Cass Terry Lawsuit 1989-1990 (open July 1, 2090) (Box 283)
      - Obstetrics and Gynecology
        - Review and Chair Change 1991-1992 (open July 1, 2022) (Box 283)
      - Otolaryngology
        - Search Committee 1992-1993 (open July 1, 2023) (Box 283)
      - Pathology
        - Personnel 1994 (open July 1, 2024) (Box 283)
        - A. Rees Midgley 1991 (open July 1, 2021) (Box 283)
      - Pharmacology
        - Grievances 1994 (open July 1, 2024) (Box 283)
      - Physical Medicine and Rehabilitation
        - Personnel 1990-1991 (open July 1, 2021) (Box 283)
      - Physiology
        - Intra-departmental Conflict 1990-1992 (open July 1, 2022) (Box 283)
      - Radiology
        - Personnel 1992-1993 (open July 1, 2023) (Box 283)
        - William Martel 1981-1993 (open July 1, 2023) (Box 283)
      - Surgery
        - Patient Information and Personnel 1990-1991, 1996 (open July 1, 2096) (Box 283)
        - Orthopedics, 1991(open July 1, 2021) (Box 283)
  - Administrative Series 1950-1998
    The Administrative Files Series of the Dean's Records subgroup began personal file kept by Deans Hubbard and Gronvall but overtime became a much more inclusive topical file. The series is subdivided into several chronological subseries reflecting the various accessions in which the records were received: 1950-1979 (original accessions) 1967-1982 (1987 accession); 1959-1984 (1990 accession); 1960-1988 (1990 #2 accession); 1960-1990 (1997 accession); and 1983-1998 (2002 accession). Within each of these subseries, the records are arranged alphabetically. There is considerable overlap in the date spans of the subseries and subject files often extend over several subseries.
    The 1950-1979 subseries of the Administrative Files series of the Dean's Records subgroup Correspondence with all senior university officials after 1959 which had previously been filed in the Deans Correspondence series.
    The Administrative Files, 1967-1982 subseries (1987 Accession) includes extensive files on the school accreditation surveys, 1967 and 1975, and the Replacement Hospital Project, 1975-1982.
    The 1959-1985 Administrative Files (1990 Accession) are arranged alphabetically and consist of materials created and received by the dean on various subjects. Committee files within the series contain materials on policies and procedures and some summaries of committee actions. The 1959-1994 (1990 #2 Accession, 3.5 linear feet) contains miscellaneous files from the deanship of John Gronvall.
    The Administrative Files 1960-1990 subseries (1997 Accession) is strongest for the period 1985-1989. The files, which document the many activities of the Medical School, include information on several initiatives such as the development of the M-CARE health maintenance organization (HMO), and the creation of the vice provost for medical affairs position. The affiliated hospitals are also well documented, particularly the severing of ties with Westland Medical Center.
    The 1983-1998 subseries of the Administrative Files (2002 accession, 25 linear feet, is comprised of the central subject files of the Medical School's Dean's Office. The subseries includes records from the tenures of dean Giles Bole (1990-1996) and interim dean A. Lorris Betz (1996-1998). It also includes earlier material, retained by Bole, handed down from the previous Medical School dean Joseph Johnson III. The series documents the major topics and issues of the era, such as the changing nature of medical education (as evidenced by a major curriculum revision covered in the files), and the increasing influence of HMOs and other managed care plans on medicine (as seen in the many files covering topics such as 'Faculty Group Practice,' 'Medical Service Plan,' and 'Networking.') Other issues reflect concerns of the larger university setting, such as the files on the indirect costs of research and implementation of Value Centered Management. Of note is the file "definitions" which is helpful in making distinctions between Medical Center, Hospital, and Medical School.
    When looking for administrative files related to the offices of Assistant and Associate Deans that were kept by the Dean's Office, researchers should note that material in the series will usually be found under the name of the administrative office. These offices include Faculty Affairs, Clinical Affairs, Medical Education, and Research. Two major exceptions are Graduate Medical Education, which was located within Research, and Minority Affairs, which was located within the Academic Programs office. It should also be noted that during the years covered by this series, the Academic Programs Office was transformed into the Student Programs Office. While the main run of the series retains the 'Academic Programs' designation, the files that have been restricted due to sensitive personnel and/or student information are filed under 'Student Programs.'
    - 1950-1979
      - A
        - General (Box 77)
        - Awards 1969 (Box 77)
      - B
        - General (Box 77)
        - Biology, Organization of in the University 1967-1968 (Box 77)
        - Budgets 1955-1956 to 1959-1960 (Box 77)
        - By-laws, Revision of Regental By-laws 1963-1969 (Box 77)
      - C
        - General (Box 77)
        - Competitive Data, Peer schools 1969-1973 (Box 77)
        - Compliance, re: Integration 1969 (see also "Integration")
          - General, 2 folders (Box 77)
          - Compliance Review of School (Box 78)
            - Negro Applicants 1966-1968 (Box 238)
          - Compliance in Departments (Box 78)
      - D
        - Dean's Staff Organization 1968-1969 (Box 78)
      - E
        - General (Box 78)
        - Enrollment Expansion 1965-1972 (Box 78)
      - F
        - Faculty Interview Format 1967 (Box 78)
        - Faculty Ranking for Non-medical Staff (Schrager-Bowden) 1974-1975 (Box 78)
        - Federal Legislation
          - 1963 (Box 78)
          - 1965 (Box 78)
          - 1967 (Box 78)
          - 1969 (Box 78)
          - 1970 (Box 78)
        - Flint TV 1965 (Box 78)
        - Funkenstein Study (admissions and curriculum) 1967-1968 (Box 78)
        - Furstenberg Tribute 1963 (Box 78)
      - G
        - General (Box 78)
        - Gerber Children's' Research Laboratory 1966-1967 (Box 78)
        - Graduate Studies, Rackham 1960-1972 (Box 78)
        - Gronvall, John A., consultant appointments (Box 78)
      - H
        - General (Box 78)
        - Health and Human Values, Report of the Task Force on 1975 (Box 78)
        - History
          - Percentage Michigan Residents in Medical Classes 1950-1968 (Box 78)
          - Form of Practice, Living Graduates, ca. 1964 (Box 78)
          - Attrition Rates 1958-1969 (Box 78)
          - Curriculum Hours by Department 1905-1962 (Box 78)
          - Space Allocation 1968 (Box 78)
          - UM and Wayne State University Estimated Teaching Responsibility 1961-1962 (Box 78)
          - Tuition Comparison 1969-1971 (Box 78)
          - Chief Administrators, Medical School 1850-1970 (Box 78)
          - Michigan Residents Entering Out of State Schools 1957-1968 (Box 78)
      - I
        - Institute for the Study of Mental Retardation 1967-1969 (Box 78)
        - Institute of Medicine Cost Study 1973 (Box 78)
        - Integration (see also "Compliance")
          - Correspondence
            - Faculty Recruitment 1962-1969 (Box 78)
            - General (external) 1962-1968 (Box 78)
            - General (internal) 1965-1970 (Box 78)
          - Statistics and Summary Information
            - 1969 Study (Box 78)
            - UM Student and House Staff Data 1962-1969 (Box 78)
            - Miscellaneous (Box 78)
          - Detroit Commission
            - 1960-1965 (Box 78)
            - 1966-1967 (Box 78)
            - 1968 (Box 78)
          - Michigan Civil Rights Commission 1969 (Box 79)
      - J
        - Junior Medical Lectures 1960 (Box 79)
      - L
        - Long Range Planning
          - Review and Comment by Walter G. Rice 1974 (Box 79)
          - Summary of Building Commitments 1970 (Box 79)
          - Background, 2 folders (Box 79)
        - Lutheran Hospital in Ann Arbor (proposed)
          - 1960-1969 (Box 79)
          - 1970-1972 (Box 79)
      - M
        - Markle Foundation
          - Correspondence 1965 (Box 79)
          - Nominations 1959-1968 (Box 79)
        - Medical Center Director, John A. Gronvall 1969-1973 (Box 79)
        - Medical Center Library 1960-1974, 3 folders (Box 79)
        - Medical School, Study of School Funding 1976-1978, 2 folders (Box 79)
        - Medical Service Plan (professional fees) (Box 80)
          - Background 1973-1974, 3 folders (Box 80)
          - Billing Program Development 1971-1972 (Box 80)
          - Dean's Working File 1971-1972, 2 folders (Box 80)
          - Departmental Responses 1971-1972 (Box 80)
          - Document for Discussion August 1973 (Box 80)
          - Interdepartmental Coordinating Committee 1972-1973 (Box 80)
          - Medical Center Organization/Quality Control 1969-1971 (Box 80)
          - Policy Issues 1971-1973 (Box 80)
          - Selected Salary Study Data 1969-1970 (Box 80)
          - Steering Committee for the Study of MSPs 1971, 2 folders (Box 80)
        - Michigan State Board of Registration in Medicine 1960-1967 (Box 80)
        - Michigan State Department of Education MD/DO 1968-1969 (Box 80)
        - Michigan State Legislature
          - Research Requests 1953 (Box 80)
          - House State Affairs Committee 1965-1966 (Box 80)
          - Senate Appropriations Committee Presentations
            - March 24, 1970 (Box 80)
            - June 16, 1971 (Box 80)
            - April 26, 1972 (Box 80)
            - May 18, 1973 (Box 80)
            - April 1, 1974 (Box 80)
            - March 5, 1975 (Box 80)
            - March 12, 1976 (Box 80)
        - Michigan State Medical Society 1966-1972 (Box 80)
        - Minority Group Study (MCAT) 1969 (Box 80)
        - Modeling Clinical Education, The Gynecology Service at University Hospital 1973 (Box 80)
        - Mott Foundation 1961 (Box 80)
      - N (Box 81)
        - National Board of Medical Examiners Examination 1958-1959 (Box 81)
        - Negro Medical Interns and Residents, Special report on 1969 (Box 81)
        - Nursery School for Handicapped Children 1964 (Box 81)
        - Nursing, School of 1960-1972 (Box 81)
      - O
        - Ojike Memorial Medical Centre, Ojikememo, Nigeria 1965-1966 (Box 81)
        - Optometry, Proposal to Establish School of 1971-1974 (Box 81)
      - P